Finding Aid for Milo Radulovich papers, 1945-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Milo Radulovich papers 1945-2008
Radulovich, Milo, 1926-2007.
1 oversized folder
6 oversized volumes
2.5 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
2008173 Aa 2; Ac
Air Force Lieutenant accused of being a security risk during the era of Senator Joseph McCarthy; records include biographical information, correspondence, scrapbooks, audio-visual materials, and other documents pertaining to the case and to the movie "Good Night, and Good Luck."
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by members of the Radulovich family (donor no. 10082 ) in 2008-2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Milo John Radulovich (October 28, 1926 -- November 19, 2007) was an American citizen (born in Detroit) of Montenegrin descent. While serving as a reserve Air Force lieutenant, Radulovich was accused of being a security risk for maintaining a "close and continuing relationship" with his father and sister who had been identified as possible "security risks", contrary to Air Force Regulation 35-62. For this, the Air Force stripped Radulovich of his commission.
The Radulovich case soon came to the attention of Edward R. Murrow, host of the popular See It Now program on CBS. For months, Murrow and producer Fred Friendly had debated on how to address Senator Joseph McCarthy's tactics. The Radulovich affair gave them an avenue. The program entitled "The Case Against Lt. Milo Radulovich, A0589839" aired on October 20, 1953. The portrayal of this man and his immigrant father led many viewers to question the impact of McCarthyist tactics for purging the government and military of potential "security risks." Radulovich was reinstated one month after the broadcast.
Radulovich moved to California where he was eventually hired by a private weather forecasting business. He later went to work for the National Weather Service, and was chief meteorologist at Capital City Airport in Lansing, Michigan when he retired in 1994.
Michael Ranville wrote a book about Radulovich's trial To Strike at a King: The Turning Point in the McCarthy Witch-Hunt. The CBS broadcast and background to its airing was dramatized in the 2005 film "Good Night, and Good Luck."
Radulovich's case is recognized by the State Bar of Michigan as one of its "Michigan Legal Milestones."
After experiencing two strokes, Radulovich died on November 19, 2007. He was awarded a posthumous degree by the University of Michigan in 2008.
The Radulovich collection consists of six series: Biographical/Personal, Security Hearing, Other Family Members, Audio/Visual Materials, Scrapbooks, and Other Materials. The collection is particularly strong in documenting the events around his hearing and the influences it caused in the succeeding decades.
Subjects:
Anti-communist movements--United States.; Clooney, George.; Good night, and good luck (Motion picture); Internal security--United States--History--20th century.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957--Influence.; Montenegrin Americans--Michigan.; Murrow, Edward R.; Radulovich, Milo, 1926-2007.; See it now (Television program)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Internal security--United States--20th century.; Radulovich family.; Radulovich, Milo, 1926-2007.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; DVDs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series documents some of Radulovich's school years, his service in the Air Force, awards and honors he received throughout the years, and some of his more general correspondence.
  - Schooling (Box 1)
    (see also oversized folder Ac)
  - Air Force
    - Security Clearance Application (Box 1)
    - Weather Squadron 1946-1952 (Box 1)
    - General 1945-1961 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors 1996-2006 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs; see also oversized folder)
  - Writings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1950s (Box 1)
      (includes letters by Fred Friendly)
    - 1960s (Box 1)
    - 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
    - 1990s-2000s (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Illness 2007 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 2007 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 2007 (oversized) (Box 3)
  - Sympathy Cards (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1953-2006 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degree (University of Michigan) 2008 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (in Montenegrin)
- Security Hearing
  The Security Hearing series documents the correspondence and publications around the time of the actual hearing. The movie "Good Night, and Good Luck" is also documented; photographs, scripts, and correspondence are included. There are some documents pertaining to McCarthyism and Edward R. Murrow in general, and the series concludes with a set of scrapbooks created by the Radulovich family.
  - Milo Radulovich Correspondence
    - June-September 1953 (Box 1)
    - October 1953 (Box 1)
    - November 1953-January 1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of others to the government about the case 1953 (Box 1)
  - Transcript of the hearing 1953 (Box 1)
    (includes supplemental brief of respondent on review of the board findings)
  - Publications
    - Magazines
      - 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - 1990-1997 (Box 2)
        (see also Box 3 for oversized material)
    - Clippings 1944, 1953-1955, 1972 (Box 2)
    - To Strike at a King (book by Michael Ranville), 1996, 2006 (Box 2)
  - McCarthyism (clippings only) 1953, 1983, 2002-2006 (Box 2)
  - "Good Night, and Good Luck" (the motion picture)
    - Correspondence March-November 2005 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Script
      - Drafts (Box 2)
      - Screenplay and History (Box 2)
      - Post Production (Box 2)
    - Cinema for Peace 2006 (Box 2)
      (some material in German)
    - Publications (Box 2)
      (see oversized folder Ac)
    - World Wide Web 2005-2008 (Box 2)
      (includes the George Clooney network and blogs written by Milo)
    - Clippings
      - Reviews (Box 2)
      - General (Box 2)
        (some material in Montenegrin)
  - Edward R. Murrow (Box 2)
    (articles remembering Murrow's journalistic influence)
  - Edward R. Murrow (Box 3)
    (oversized articles remembering Murrow's journalistic influence)
- Other Family Members
  A few relatives are briefly documented in the Other Family Members series, including his mother Ikonija.
  - Nada 1983, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Milina Jovanovic (Box 2)
  - Slava (family annual ritual) (Box 2)
  - History (Box 2)
    (includes photographs)
  - Correspondence
    - Ikonija (Milo's mother) 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1998, 2007-2008 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook Documents (Box 2)
- Audio/Visual Materials
  The Audio/Visual Materials series contains a mix of video and audio recordings. Included are: taped personal conversations relating to the case, NPR interviews, and some material about Murrow and other notables of the period.
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    includes images that have been printed
  - "News Reel History, Clips From Murrow/McCarthy, West America", VHS tape (Box 2)
  - "The Spartan Podcast-Mike Ranville and Milo Radulovich 2005", CD (Box 2)
  - Audiocassettes
    (description provided by donor)
    - Ratkovic and Radulovich, Conversation re: case (Box 2)
      (personal conversation regarding legal options)
    - Interview with Eric Hoffer 1967 (Box 2)
      (rebroadcast of the Eric Sevareid interviewing the American social writer)
    - Edward R. Murrow February 11, 1977 (Box 2)
      (radio show remembering Murrow's journalistic contributions)
    - Milo-Ranville March 1993 (Box 2)
      (gathering information for his book; includes Milo's sister)
    - Fred and Ruth Friendly/Ranville April 1993 (Box 2)
      (gathering information for his book)
    - Ann Arbor NPR, Todd Mundt Show, Interview with Milo and M. Ranville March 27, 1998 (Box 2)
    - NPR interview Grant/Milo from Mark Steiner, Baltimore October 26, 2005, 2 tapes (Box 2)
      (about the movie which Grant was a co-writer and co-producer)
  - DVDs
    - "An Evening with Milo Radulovich and Mike Ranville December 1, 1997" (Box 2)
      (Ranville recounts the story with video clips; 100 minutes)
    - "John F. Faulk Conference April 17, 1997" (Box 2)
      (Part I: intro, inventing TV news, pioneering broadcast news; Part II: To Strike a King, Murrow and Radulovich case, full panel discussion)
    - "The Capitol Brief, Tim Skubick" (Box 2)
      (film and interviews from Michigan Milestone event at MSU, September 1998; 12 minutes)
    - "26th Michigan Legal Milestone September 2, 1998" (Box 2)
      (Dedication speeches for unveiling of monument at MSU College of Law; 2 hours)
    - "An Evening with Milo Radulovich at Wayne State University November 27, 2001" (Box 2)
      (hosted by Jack Lessenberry, panel, students, family and friends conversation; 2 hours)
    - "Michigan Senate Chambers November 13, 2003" (Box 2)
      (Presentation of Senate Resolution 198 to Radulovich and Judge Sanborn)
    - "Good Night, and Good Luck" 2005 (Box 2)
    - "Milo Memorial Detroit January 27, 2008" (Box 2)
      (audio only)
    - "MCBA (Macomb County Bar Association) Celebrating 100 Years" (Box 2)
      (Address of Milo Radulovich honoring his friend and attorney Kenneth Sanborn)
- Scrapbooks: "The Case of Milo Radulovich", 6 volumes
  The Scrapbooks series is a set of six volumes created by the Radulovich family entitled "The Case of Milo Radulovich." The series follows a general chronological order and contains clippings, photographs, memorabilia, and other such materials. Each volume includes a detailed index, clippings, photographs, programs, memorabilia, etc.
  - 1953-1954 (Volume 1)
  - 1954-1994 (Volume 2)
  - 1992-2005 "The Book (To Strike a King) and the Movie ('Good Night, and Good Luck')" (Volume 3)
  - 2005-2006 "The Reviews, the Awards, the Companion Book" (Volume 4)
  - 2006 "Movie Awards, Macomb Bar Association, and More" (Volume 5)
  - 2007 "Born October 28, 1926, Died November 19, 2007" (Volume 6)
- Other Materials
  - Photocopies of clippings and correspondence relating to Milo Radulovich on file at the Burton Historical Collections (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous regarding Ikonija Radulovic (Box 4)
  - Photographs of celebration at the Bentley Library prior to the University of Michigan degree ceremony, December 12, 2008 (Box 4)